Guide to the William Friedberg Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
William Friedberg Papers,
1950-1965.
Friedberg, William, 1916-1965.
5.72 linear feet ( 11 document boxes, oversize box).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
6796315
William “Billy” Friedberg (1916-1965) is best remembered as a television comedy writer, although he also wrote plays, musicals, variety reviews, short stories, and radio programs. Among his best-known works are episodes of "Car 54, Where Are You?", "As Time Goes By", and "The Phil Silvers Show". Friedberg's work represented in this collection spans many genres, including comedy review sketches, TV dramas, short stories, plays, and musicals.
Biographical Note
William “Billy” Friedberg (1916-1965) was a New York theatre publicity agent who began writing and then producing television during the 1950s and early 1960s. He is best remembered as a television comedy writer, although he also wrote plays, musicals, variety reviews, short stories, and radio programs. Among his best-known works are episodes of "Car 54, Where Are You?", "As Time Goes By", and "The Phil Silvers Show". In 1957 and 1958, the Academy of Television Arts and Sciences awarded Friedberg the Emmy for Best Comedy Writing of a Variety or Situation Comedy, for "The Phil Silvers Show"; he was nominated for the same award again in 1959. He collaborated on a few television scripts with writer Neil Simon, worked on various television programs with producers Nat Hiken and Max Liebman, and wrote routines for comedians such as Alan King and Martha Raye. His television work began in the period of review and variety programs sponsored by large corporations, and evolved into the era of the long-running serial drama or sitcom. Later in his career he served as a producer for a few television series, including "Harry's Girls". He was married briefly in 1945 to actress Jane Hoffman, and then from 1950-1965 to actress Hope Cameron. Friedberg died of a heart attack at the age of 49.
Scope and Content
Friedberg's work represented in this collection spans many genres, including comedy review sketches, TV dramas, short stories, plays, and musicals. The vast majority of the collection consists of typed scripts, either drafts or “shooting scripts” used for production, which Friedberg wrote or produced. Production files for some of the scripts are the second-largest group of material, including casting ideas, budgets, contracts, advertising records, and intra-staff memos. The collection also contains documents which Friedberg used in his creative process, including typed or handwritten notes and ideas for future works, and newspaper clippings that he used for inspiration. Three sketchbooks of pencil drawings are also present, which may be the work of Friedberg's wife Hope Cameron. Finally, there are a small number of family snapshots and personal papers.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series.
Series I: Writings and Work, 1950-1965, undated
Series II: Personal, 1950-1965
Subjects
Friedberg, William, 1916-1965.; Hiken, Nat.; King, Alan, 1927-2004.; Liebman, Max.; Raye, Martha.; Simon, Neil.; Dramatists, American--20th century.; Radio serials.; Radio programs--United States.; Screenwriters--United States.; Television authorship.; Television--Production and direction.; Television scripts.; Theater--United States--History--20th century.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Donated by the estate of Hope Cameron Friedberg, 1999.
- Series I: Writings and Work of Billy Friedberg, 1950-1965, undated
  This series consists of Friedberg’s writings, organized by genre, and documents that supported the creative process and production of his dramatic work (drafts, notes, contracts, budgets, etc.). Also included are production documents of the television programs that he produced. Material in this series is arranged alphabetically. When multiple episodes of a program are included, they are arranged in chronological order.
  - Subseries I.1: Television, 1950-1965
    This subseries contains Friedberg’s television scripts arranged in alphabetical order by the show’s title, together with documents such as Friedberg’s notes, intra-staff memos, budgets, and other records of production.
    - Allen King Show
      - Notes and Memos, 1960 (Box 1)
      - Script Drafts, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
      - Script, Shooting, and Documentation, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - As Time Goes By
      - Notes and Scenario, circa 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Script--Early Drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Script--Pilot, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bob and Ray Show, The
      - Scripts 1952 March-April (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Scripts 1952 May-June (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Scripts 1952 July (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Scripts 1952 July-August (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Scripts, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Buick Circus Hour, The --Scripts, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Car 54, Where Are You?
      - Scripts # 31-38, circa 1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Scripts # 42-45, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Scripts # 46-47, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Colgate Comedy Hour, The --Script, 1952 December (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Drumbeater, The --Scripts, circa 1959 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Harry's Girls --Documentation, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Jack Carson Review, The
      - Scripts 1950 October-November (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Scripts 1950 December (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Scripts 1951 January-February (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Scripts 1951 April-May (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Scripts 1951 June-September (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Scripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Law and Mr. Jones, The --Scripts and Documentation, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Leave it to Larry
      - Scripts # 1-2, 1952 October (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Scripts # 3,4, and 6, 1952 October-November (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Scripts # 7, 9, 1952 December (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Magnificent Montague, The --Pilot Script, circa 1957 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Martha Raye Show, The
      - Scripts, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Scripts, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Scripts, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Scripts, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Scripts, 1953, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
      - Scripts, 1954, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
      - Max Liebman Presents
      - Script, 1954 October 10 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Script, 1954 October 23 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Script, 1954 November (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Script, 1955 January (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Script, 1955 April 9 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Script, 1955 April 24 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Script, 1955 May (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - McKeever and the Colonel --Shooting Schedules, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - NBC News Broadcast--Script, 1954 April (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - NBC Presents Betty and Jane Kean --Script, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Old Man Webster
      - Notes and Correspondence, circa 1961 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Script Drafts, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Perry Como Show, The --Script, 1960 April (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Peter Loves Mary --Shooting Schedule, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Phil Silvers Show, The (aka "Sergeant Bilko")--Documentation, 1957-1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - [Satin and Spurs ]--Script, circa 1954 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Shirley --script, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Three's Company --Scenarios and Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - U.S. Rubber Company Presents U.S. Royal Showcase --Script, 1952 January (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Subseries I.2: Radio, 1950-1951
    Included in this subseries are the scripts of fifty-one episodes of the radio serial “The Magnificent Montague” in chronological order. These aired in 1950-1951, and several years later (circa 1957) Friedberg wrote a pilot script for an adaptation of the series into a television program, included in Subseries I.1. The series title is also the name of a popular African-American disc jockey of the late 1950s and the 1960s; however, they seem to be unrelated.
    - Magnificent Montague, The
      - Scripts # 1-4, 1950 November-December (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - Scripts # 5-9, 1950 December - 1951 January (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Scripts # 10-14, 1951 January-February (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Scripts # 15-19, 1951 February-March (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Scripts # 20-24, 1951 March-April (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Scripts # 25-29, 1951 April-May (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Scripts # 30-34, 1951 June (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Scripts # 35-39, 1951 June-August (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Scripts # 40-44, 1951 August-September (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Scripts # 45-49, 1951 September-October (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Scripts # 50-51, 1951 October (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Subseries I.3: Other Writings and Work, 1953-1963, undated
    This subseries comprises all other genres of writing by Friedberg, including plays, musicals, and short stories, and unidentified writings and fragments, in alphabetical order by genre. Included are writings generated in the creative process: ideas for future projects that either did not come to fruition or are not included here in their finished form, and clippings that he used for inspiration. The subseries contains a group of memos from director Robert Soderberg, who collaborated with Friedberg on the television programs “Peter Loves Mary” and “McKeever and the Colonel.” Also present is the text for a course on acting in commercials, titled “TV Commercials University” -- it is unclear whether Friedberg taught this class (and thus, wrote this text) or participated as a student.
    - Clippings--Inspiration, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Memos--Soderberg, Robert, 1960-1962 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - New Projects--Notes and Scenarios, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Plays--Scripts and Supporting Documentation (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Scripts--Other Authors, 1953-1963 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Short Stories--Drafts, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - T.V. Commercials University --Classroom Text, circa 1958 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Untitled Writings and Script Fragments, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Series II: Personal, circa 1950-1965
  This series holds a folder of letters from Neil Simon, written circa 1964 when Simon was in London; most of the contents are personal, chronicling Simon’s experience living in England, but he also occasionally touches on various professional projects, both his own and Friedberg’s. This series contains a “General” folder of personal papers such as letters, contracts, clippings about Friedberg, and a resume. Series II also includes two unidentified photos, probably of Friedberg, and a caricature of him by an unknown artist. Lastly, it houses three sketchbooks of pencil drawings, artist unknown, although two are marked “Hope” on the cover, suggesting that they may have belonged to Friedberg’s wife, Hope Cameron. Items are arranged alphabetically by material type, after the General folder.
  - General--Correspondence, Documents, and Clippings, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Caricature of Billy Friedberg, undated, artist unknown (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Simon, Neil--Correspondence, circa 1964 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbooks (3), undated (Box 11, Folder 5)